so I've got some gathered some questions
uh in terms of
vinaya precepts hmm
keeping the precepts
so sometimes people take the precepts
because of circumstances
yet if the circumstances change so does
their precepts
and others take it on because they
understand that it is beneficial
regardless of circumstances
either way will both types of people be
able to attain Purity in terms of virtue
purity of Mind purity of view resulting
in Freedom from suffering
no it needs to be taken away
because one one person's is keeping the
precepts he's keeping the vinaya
he's keeping the vinaya
due to circumstances but yeah for 50
years yeah
doesn't really step out of that it's
it's it's meritorious as it would have
said he's not engaging with centrality
the way you would if you don't keep the
precepts but in and of itself yeah that
does not result in mind
um turning away from centrality
um
gaining an insight into the nature of
non-ownership and everything else that
you need to you need to keep the trees
brightly
and that we spoke about it and that
keeping the principle is basically
whether you keep them with the
responsibility for the precepts that's
what determines whether you keep them
rightly or not
so taking the precepts as a result of a
tradition culture
external values and that or it must be
done because of that
means that's where the responsibility is
it's on this level of external Acts
and that's why the mind is still bound
with them
sure they're better act than
non-percepts but
I keep the precepts because I choose to
do so because I want to train my mind
because of the weight of the tradition
of the culture that then brings it much
closer to home
and it's harder to keep the precepts
that way because you realize
I can choose to not keep them
it's on me there is no external
Authority or criteria or weight
it's just it's on me so I can I can do
it or not do it and then you feel that
oh so then why am I doing it well
exactly so feeling the keeping of the precepts
so feeling the keeping of the precepts
on that level with that responsibility
and not breaking them on that level with
that responsibility
and sustaining the context of keeping
them yet that is now directly affecting
your mind the person who takes them
responsibly or chooses to take on the
precepts sees where the problem is
sees where the problem is
already they see or I'm responsible for
my mind being in it depressed
my mind being unhappy what can I do
about it yeah sure they can they could
they could I need to take on the
precepts that is that is the only
sort of right beginning yeah you see
that a direct
possibility that or at least have faith
that there is a direct possibility so
you don't then mask the presets and I do
it just because we all agree to do it
and I'm fine as long as I stick to our
external agreement I'm fine I don't have
to think about anything else I don't
have to reveal my intentions further
I'm fine I'm doing it I'm meeting the
requirements following the phone
I'm blameless yeah all of that but it's
like no no
you're blameless if your intentions are
not rooted in video version delusion and
in order to start revealing your
intentions you need to start keeping the
precepts on that intentional level every
single time like I don't know I'm I'm
abstaining from breaking the precept I'm
abstaining from Central acts acts of
carelessness or anger because I choose
to do so because I want to train my mind
not because and that's why then you
wouldn't be bothered if say
we well we agreed to keep this
priesthood and now you're not you're
just going doing your own thing it
doesn't affect it's not my problem
because I'm not defined by the group
think nor group action I'm defined by my
own intentions every single time
also you're probably less likely to I
mean uh put the responsibility for like your
uh put the responsibility for like your
State of Mind on other people like I'm
depressed
you're more likely to see where the
responsibility yeah you're closer to
recognize where the problem is yeah
so it's kind of helpful to be in a
community of people who keep precepts
yeah but the Dane the dangers there is
they're relying on the community
for you keeping the peace yeah it's
helpful to be in the community to keep
the precepts
but not necessarily helpful to be in a
community to keep the precepts but there
never really points at where the
you know responsibility should be and
teaches you what you need to know
so if you're in community that keeps the
precepts due to the external
circumstances and the authority and
that's all they do and then when it
comes to practice the views are like
here and there
and nothing brings you back to take on
responsibility for those precepts that's
not helpful now you're going to prolifer
it even more because I'm sure many of
the Aesthetics and brahmins in the
sutras were virtuous in terms of the
precepts yet they were extremely you know like
yet they were extremely you know like
victims of extremely wrong views they're
the Buddha himself like you know quite
harshly mocked or dismissed or
dismantled but yeah many of them were
probably quite uh quite restrained in
that sense
so
that see if somebody joins that sort of
community whereby you would be
restrained but then with all these views
that do not reveal the responsibility or
undo it just add further to it well that
would be even harder to undo now then if
you go along with it of course you could
be responsible in your context I mean it
always remains possible you can always
turn around
um but it's going to be factually harder
because now you are
accumulating these these further views
on account of already that
non-responsibility of your of your
precepts and The Virtue but if you're in
a community that keeps the preset and it
keeps teaching you how to take the
responsibility for it and not rely on
the community
and recognize your own intentions and
the the roots of it yeah that's like
okay now see the presets have been taken
even if they haven't been taken rightly
now they've resulted in greater
perspective that it's making you take it
rightly and that's the gradual training
if they come and dwell restrained by
this this these are the virtue of the
precepts a person starts doing it rightly okay
a person starts doing it rightly okay
now God sends those now increase okay
there's a now be mindful with all the
instruction yeah there is a suit that says the
yeah there is a suit that says the
danger of
like uh
will relying on another person like you
the danger of you your precept your
practice being Reliant your well-being
yeah your equilibrium yeah yeah someone
else doing that same stuff
because if that person that monk does
all of a sudden changes and does a
defiled act um
and the Sangha here he has to disrobe or
something then yeah
well that's like my faith all my
inspirations yeah
yeah
one on the standing on each other's
shoulder he's like oh you look after me
I look after you I was like no no
actually the safest will be if you like
to you look after yourself and I look
after myself
and then we're both going to be in sync
let's do it further
[Music] another question is I am afraid of
another question is I am afraid of
breaking vinaya
I obsess over the Minor Details
and having now read that the Buddha
in his last instructions said to the
monks after I am gone the Sangha if it
once May abolish the Lesser and minor
training rules
so it seems that I have been obsessing
over things which are not important
I think I should obsess over what is
important but I don't know which
guidelines to now obsess over
if the Buddha himself says the minor
lesser training ruler can be abolished
if you want hmm
[Music] exactly so then you have to accept the
exactly so then you have to accept the
fact that
there is fear in your mind
when I can't do with your obsession
and they're not decked out of fear
except he didn't endured it
oh they're all these rules am I breaking
oh I'm afraid I'm doubtful feels
unpleasant so I keep acting towards
re-clarifying and rehashing all these
rules and permutations so then I can
remove the doubt
and that's why
you're afraid and that's why you're in
doubt and that's why
you're not uh
benefiting from keeping the precepts
so you have to recognize that it's like
yeah but I'm not great in the precepts
the mind is making think and rehash and
recheck can go into Minor Details the
Buddha himself said you could abolish
all the minor and lesser rules just keep
the main projectors inside and diseases
or whatever
uh that terrifies me now because it
basically now that doubt that I've been
feeding through trying to redefine and
and re like rehash the the same answers
over and over again oh it's mad because
because he was never there but yes so
you need to stop acting out of the doubt
trying to get rid of it through you know
revisiting the text and re-clarifying
what you already know and accept the
fact that you already know what a
precepts are
you're not breaking them and the mind is
being irrational and resisting and
trying to make you act towards it and
and and overwhelm you and you have to do
that and not act because that Suitor
said when the Buddhist uh in the Paris
when he's passing away and he says he
doesn't clarify which are the minor
rules that you can abolish so that but I
think it's great because it does leave
responsibility on each person after we
passed away Ananda reported that and
then all these other hands was like
guessing or rather suggesting it's like
okay well I think okay I think that we
can we can abandon everything except for
grave offenses then another hand said no
no I think we can abandon everything
except the four grave offenses and some
decisors then somebody says well let's
include this let's not include that but
generally he was like oh just just this
just wipe all of it except the four big
wipe all of it except the four big
barajakas because that's enough for the
training from where they were other
Huntsville actually
it wasn't just they were trying to get
rid of the rules no they knew what was
valuable for the practice
so that's kind of and and then obviously
they said well that's not for now at
least let's not abolish any of it
because the Buddha just passed away
there are many people that already know
our rules and they'll say look as soon
as the teacher died they are kind of
dismissing his training
and there was a factual kind of Reason
back then because the Buddha did just
pass away and everybody was aware of it
but today you can use it like just even
for yourself to reflect and kind of
okay so if they're like these other
hands they said I mean they would not
win it to begin with when monks started
practicing they knew what to do they
knew what not to do anything rooted in
create a version the illusion but as
things started you know as things were
becoming more diluted things were
proliferated and then certain rules
needed to be defined just certain
criteria to to remind you of where not
to go
uh but yeah so it's like whether and if
you're acting out of a mind of Doubt
even if you had just one rule you could
become irrational about it
let alone if you have many more
but the point is that you are feeding
that mind of doubt that it's making you
even more afraid of breaking even more
of this even when you're not breaking it
because you keep trying to get rid of
the discomfort of the doubt through
justifications of the external Authority
the text the tradition oh please urgent
tell me I'm not wrong okay thank you now
I'm not wrong no you are wrong even if
he told you not wrong you're wrong
because you acted out of doubt that's
why you still feel and that's where
you're still Bound by those external
things that are kind of covering up your
own responsibility you need the external
Authority clarification the text the
letter to make you feel safe
but that's not where the safety comes
from safety comes from not being moved
by unsafety
so by doubt which is unsafe fear is
unsafe I must clarify so I'm safe no
that's why you will remain unsafe
I must not act out of it so that I can
become safe and then I don't need the
tradition or the texts or even the
Buddha himself that's what it says like
in the soothers that's it
you are your own guide now when you get
the right view you don't even need
Buddha's input of course it's valuable
to have it it would speed up your
progress but it's not necessary
visit advice of seeing the danger in the
slightest fault yeah so so where's the
fault here
is The Fault in this
hundred sort of in 50th permutation of
this letter no the fault is in the
intention of greed ill will distraction
that's the fault so see the danger in it
that's it you cannot break any rules you
can you can you can externally not break
any rules but still act out of greed
yeah of course but that's exactly what
happens when the responsibility when the
responsibilities on the tradition or the
community there is no uh
revealing of your own intentions and
that's when you start having all these
loopholes in vinay oh I can do this with
the fault sorry revealing of the folks
basically sorry I don't there's no revealing yeah
sorry I don't there's no revealing yeah
exactly right right
you might be revealing the what you
think Faults Are but that's not really
the false it pertain to gradual training
the point what I was going to say was
you if when the responsibility is
projected on the tradition
then you're not seeing your intentions
which means now uh anything that's not
defined or I can do it because see the
rule defines like this which means this
is allowable because it hasn't so you're
already not having a context on account
of it and now because you think well
because you think that what you should
or shouldn't do is defined by the letter
not by your intention
you'll be doing things that are
unsuitable but are not necessarily
explicitly forbidden by the letter or
the culture or the tradition
so you will develop like even worse this
kind of discrepancy or that existential
level where but you think you are pure
because look I'm blameless I do
everything right while at the same time
it actually more impure because of your
views and because of further masking
away of your own intentions
so what should as this question says
what should the person obsess over
slightest fault
slightest fault of acting out of
hindrances acting out of greed aversion distraction
acting out of greed aversion distraction
doubt that's the fault the fault is
you're trying to get rid of the pain of
doubt through
placing the authority on the external
things of tradition books
definitions and so on and again senior
monks and so the only way you can do
something and also is to act out of and
wholesome intentions yeah you know you
might you might even break mine minor
Rules by mistake or you know to
circumstantial but if you act out of
unwholesome yeah that's not a fault yeah
the fault is when you act out a great
diversion delusion even you know within
the vineyard within the precepts that is
still the fault
and in the video there are so many rules
which are predicated on the intention
behind it yeah those are the ones that
matter really like there's so many rules
that are kind of circumstantial and like
you know simply not you can't even
you can't even fathom how they would be
applicable or something
because the circumstances have changed
so much but then you have the rules of
yeah if the intentions are this that's
why it's an offense oh so if you're
already projected on the level of
external cultural Authority tradition
for the definition of my rules means
that whole factor of intention
determining whether it's an offense or
not becomes invisible
because you read that oh well if if you
have intention rooted in last tenets and
offense if it wasn't rooted in last it wasn't an
if it wasn't rooted in last it wasn't an
offense
what book can you tell me whether my
intention agent can you tell me can you
can can this community tell me please
tell me because and then you realize oh
you can't solve that doubt in that
manner because intention cannot be found
in external Authority
so what do you do then well you ignore
the factor of intention and start
creating own rules within your own
tradition in the culture they would then
prevent even a possibility of doubting
my own intentions and that takes you
even further away from where the
practice is
doubting your intentions is good
it's unpleasant but it's useful
and it can actually reveal where the
real problem is you trying to get
through the discomfort of the doubt
you're acting out of hindrances
you not being able to remain unmoved
even when you know
no my intention was good yeah but still
and you get perturbed because the mind
is undeveloped and now you start acting
towards it and you ignore what you know
and start trying to just irrationally
get rid of the pain of the doubt that
well but wait maybe there's always Maybe
if but you're the one who has to draw a
line and then not cross it through
acting out of it and that's how then the
mind will come down not otherwise
there's another related question I don't
know uh in terms of assumption to Virtue and
uh in terms of assumption to Virtue and
Duty or attachment to Virtue Duty
so the question is what exactly is the
Assumption there
uh
and this
I think this assumption that this virtue
and Duty in itself will result in safety
so a person can I'm not gonna do what I
want to do anymore I'm just going to
follow this community these rules
and forget about myself which means I am
uprooting sense of self
just following the rules of the
community and doing what the rules are
thus no self completely humble and purified
no self completely humble and purified
if I just stick to these prescribed
rules of this particular Community hmm
in it
yeah that's basically as if it's still
finding safety in the external form but
that's ignoring yourself you kind of
block yourself in yeah that's what I
mean it's worse in a way yeah because
you are adopting these views now
that are Sheltering you even more than
before and it will be harder for you to
give them up because it will be then you
have to experience that non-safety twice
as much as you would have otherwise if
you didn't go down that rabbit hole of
masking responsibility
and if you as I say in in the Buddhist
monastic context you you have so many
different types of Buddhism
and if there's another group of Buddhist
monastics they do something slightly
different it's a kind of threat
to you
that's why I guess like schisms can
arise because yeah I'm attached to my
Community well that's why it's almost
wrong yeah that's why it almost happened
I'm attached to my assumed safety
or the thing that gives me safety and
this is a threat yeah yeah I'm attaching
basically I'm I am bound with that external
I'm I am bound with that external
self-justifying righteous point of view
but this is the right thing that's not
the right thing
and and that's all it takes
that's all it takes
you're finding safety in that external
righteousness in the same sense you will
find safety in the external Authority
the external tradition and now you you
found what nobody else understood on
that external level and now you are the
right one and that's it that's why it's
a problem
even if
but your fund safety is factually
correct say it's the Buddha's words the matter
say it's the Buddha's words the matter
you took it in that external uh
self-righteous sense
you haven't actually uh righteous yeah
you haven't endured it internally on the
right level
and that's why when when the when the
monks were falling out almost there
let's kiss them over like some vinaya
rule about the salt or whatever it was
when the Buddha came
told him like okay you got to stop this
now it's getting out of hand and they
sort of dismissed him three times he
said well don't you worry about it it's
all coming or your camera they dismissed
the person
that Define the rule
on account of which they feel
self-righteous and he tells them you're
both wrong now and they dismiss him
because that's how intoxicating
self-righteousness is they dismiss the
Buddha on account of
whom they're practicing the whole thing
they became monks he defined the rules
he tells them okay that's not important
doesn't matter you you mind your own
business basically that's how
intoxicating it is it was
even even back then
because it is rooted in that sense of
safety that sense of righteousness
and obviously for somebody who has been
uh already keeping the precepts in that
manner of the external Authority and
then just redefining that righteousness
the clarity to gain the more
righteousness oh yeah well you know you
I know Pali and I know the etymology of
it well I know Paulie I know what the
language before Pali well I know the
language before before that and and so I
have the thread further than you
none of that that's already complete
loss of context because is that where
you find intentions your intentions for
actions in dictionaries and languages
and studying of etymologies now that's
always going to be here and now and
that's going to be the reason why you're
looking at these places now that you're
obviously unaware of the reason you're
unawero so yes there needs to be some definition
so yes there needs to be some definition
some place that's what eight precepts
ten precepts that's that's pretty much
the kind of the framework
that's what covers the non uh the the
actions they would they would take you
to centrality and ill will and so on so
you don't act towards those things
everything else sure
if you see a direct direct relation
direct benefits to taming the mind you
recognize it but and and that's how you
will not be dependent on anywhere in the
world even if they say oh none of these
rules matter or all these rules matter
no you have a direct line to what
matters what's fault and what isn't
fault which is your own intentions that
you have been uprooting rightly and not
acting out of hindrances and doubt and
trying to get rid of them and falling
back onto the external Authority for
safety because it is still the same external
because it is still the same external
Authority somebody might turn to says
that's my authority somebody won't do
that for whatever personal preferences
but it will study the language upon
language upon language upon language and
discern the connections that nobody else
seen and that is my safety now see that
is the unique thing there that's clearly
defined inaccessible to doubt
until somebody says well actually that
paper came later then what you think and
it's not before but it was after that's
it you're undermined already so what do
you do to revisit everything you have to
revisit everything exactly so it's not
safe it's only only a relative safety
because you placed it in a place you put
in a place that's not actually safe and
can never be safe
and it's kind of addictive as well if
you have
found safety in in that in the past yeah
you will be seeking in the same way if
it's undermined okay now I need to well
that's why it's still about paramas it's
one of the first three factors it's a
factual real fetter so